Leah: Listening does not always get
classed as a communication skill,
but it can be one of the most
important skills, which can have a
major impact on job effectiveness
and relationships with others.
We use listening to obtain
information and to learn, so that
we can process and understand that
information and utilise our skills
in interpreting and acting on it.
However, we don’t always hear
everything that is be said to us
especially if we are distracted.
Jack: The way to improve our listening
skills is by ‘active listening’ where
a conscious effort is made to take
on board the complete message that
is being communicated, as well as
the words that the person is saying.
It is a way of listening that
keeps a person involved with their
conversation partner in a positive way.
In order to practice ‘active listening’
a person needs to pay careful attention
to what is being said making the
other person feel that they are being
listened to and not get distracted
by anything else around them.
They must also keep focussed
on what is being said without
getting bored or losing interest.
Leah: ‘Active listening’ also serves the
purpose of earning the trust of others
and having the opportunity to offer
support and empathy to the speaker.
‘Active listening’ is particularly
important when a person is
in a supervisory position or
interacting with colleagues.
It helps with understanding problems
and collaboration on projects.